Contact

hassan.239@osu.edu

www.linkedin.com/in/arafathassan1 (LinkedIn) arafathassan1.github.io (Portfolio)

Top Skills

ArcGIS Python API
Computer-Aided Design (CAD)
Building Information Modeling (BIM)

Languages

Bengali (Professional Working) English (Full Professional) Spanish (Limited Working)

Certifications

Workflows

ArcGIS Enterprise: Configuring a
Base Deployment
Futura GIS II
Process Data from Dirty to Clean
Analyze Data to Answer Questions

ArcGIS Enterprise: Administration

Arafat Hassan

Database Administration Specialist 2 (GIS) at Ohio Department of Natural Resources

Columbus, Ohio, United States

Summary

Earned a Bachelor of Science (BS) focused in Geographic Information Science and a minor focusing in City and Regional Planning from The Ohio State University. Skilled in administering/managing databases and using GIS/visualization related softwares such as ESRI ArcGIS tools, ERDAS Imagine, QGIS, Tableau, etc. Continuously learning programming languages such as JAVA, HTML, Arcade Expressions, Python, R Programming, etc. Extensively experienced in Microsoft Office (Excel, Word, Powerpoint, etc.), Google Drive, ETL process, retail, and customer service.

Experience

Ohio Department of Natural Resources
Database Administration Specialist 2 (GIS)
March 2023 - Present (1 year 1 month)
Columbus, Ohio, United States

- Manage, identify, and implement in SSMS/ArcSDE (Enterprise Geodatabase) any improvements that can be implemented in department-wide ArcSDE for optimal performance for GIS users by rebuilding indexes, clearing archived records, updating statistics, compressing via scripts, etc
- Manage and coordinate the maintenance of department-wide non-spatial database systems (SQL Server) using SQL Server Jobs in SQL Server Mangement Studio (SSMS)
- Plan, implement, and enhance new divisional geo-spatial database items such as vector and raster datasets
- Create new and enhances existing database elements in ArcSDE and nonspatial database with triggers, stored procedures, replication, etc
- Assist coworkers, different GIS departmental representatives, interns with any ArcSDE needs including updating schema, implementing attribute rules, automate tasks via scripts, creating views in SSMS, etc
- Document and diagram existing database environments, policies, and process for recordkeeping

City of Westerville Systems Analyst/GIS Administrator February 2022 - March 2023 (1 year 2 months)

Westerville, Ohio, United States

- Develop short and long-range plans, goals, objectives and priorities to improve city's operational efficiency and effectiveness for GIS development and integrations
- Communicate with GIS users to determine current and future needs, and implements recommendations such as building a custom printing widget for WebGIS
- Maintain and monitor the health of the GIS servers including performing monthly updates for both ArcGIS Enterprise and ArcGIS Online
- Develop, administer, and maintain GIS web sites and applications for the internet and intranet
- Performs continuous updates of city's core GIS data and web site information
- Communicate with the general public, vendors, management, and contractors in order to coordinate GIS projects and administer the use of data such as Tyler Technologies: New World, FuturaGIS, etc.
- Represent the GIS team on committees and task forces by serving as a technical advisor in the exchange of information or in addressing specific needs
- Prepare, process, and review written documents pertaining to GIS to ensure compliance with departmental policies and procedures
- Prioritize and track time-sensitive projects and assignments to ensure timely completion
- Coordinate and oversee various special projects and/or presentations in support of the GIS system including transitioning from current aerial imagery provider, giving GIS presentation at the Citizens Academy, etc.
- Establish and maintain effective working relationships with superiors, fellow workers, and vendor's representatives
- Review programs, white-papers, research papers, attend training courses, attend GIS Steering Committee meetings, etc. to develop innovative approaches to problem solving and to make recommendations
- Develop, document, and provide GIS standards, training and guidance for GIS users within the City of Westerville

NiSource GIS Technician January 2021 - February 2022 (1 year 2 months) Columbus, Ohio, United States

- Analyze design capital project completion information by reviewing proper pressure tests, materials, and facilities to assure compliance with proposed engineering designs, company policies, practices, standards and other applicable codes
- Update/maintain GIS and work management system to accurately reflect gas system updates using given project as-built and related documentations
- Execute capital projects including providing new gas service to new customers, public roadway improvements and relocations, gas system improvement and maintenance in a timely manner that adheres with the department metrics
- Provide technical assistance and build strong relationship through communication and collaboration with Field Engineering, Construction, M&R, and Field Operation staff
- Proactively collaborate with leaders, co-workers, and key business partners with planning group goals, objectives, and priorities to exceed department metrics
- Assist co-workers with executing their capital projects
- Guide Field Operation staff to provide accurate information for non-capital work to capital work
- Actively reaching out to participate on upcoming department projects such as beta testing migration from ArcMap to ArcGIS Pro and accurately mapping customer service lines
- Continuously learning about upcoming GIS news and tools to keep up with the industry standards and expand personal knowledge

City of Canton, Ohio
GIS Analyst/Engineering Technician I
May 2019 - January 2021 (1 year 9 months)
Canton, Ohio

- Maintain and update enterprise GIS databases with new/existing water distribution system data in a Geometric Network
- Perform quality assurance for the water distribution system data from multiple sources (field workers, historical records, engineering drawing, and AutoCAD drawings)
- Initiator of the organizational system that keeps records of the waterline projects including creating As-Builts drawings and end of the year cost reports
- Utilization of ArcGIS Pro to append data between databases
- Apply hosted feature layers in ArcGIS Pro to append next day assignments in Workforce for ArcGIS of water assets verification for interns

- Generates custom feature layers in ArcGIS Pro through digitizing to then be published as a web layer in ArcGIS Online for future presentations
- Creates web maps and applications such as dashboards by utilizing ArcGIS Online
- Utilization of Workforce for ArcGIS, Collector, and Survey123 app to perform GPS data collection
- Performs in field data collection of GPS data from new/replaced water valves, fire hydrants, curb stops, and fittings using Trimble products
- Collaborates with supervisors to plan current or next GIS project/agenda
- Provides teaching and mentorship to GIS interns
- Assists with tech support to field workers and help fix troubleshoots with the county GIS Department

Delaware County, Ohio GIS Planner Intern September 2018 - April 2019 (8 months) Delaware, Ohio

- Assisted with converting and modifying county shapefiles from ArcView 3.2
 to ArcMap 10.6
- "Import from ArcView" ArcMap extension
- Store texts/annotations including road names in a geodatabase with correct fonts and its size
- Match queries, map symbols, shapefile names, legends, title, scale bar, neatlines, north arrow in ArcMap with ArcView
- Combined converted map with updated geodatabase text annotations to export it to a PDF file
- Collaborated with supervisors to update and maintain the county maps such as new zoning, removing silvers or gaps of polygons

Sprint

Retail Sales Consultant December 2017 - April 2019 (1 year 5 months)

- Assisted customers with their cellular needs through creating bundles that works for them.
- Exceeded key performance objectives, including sales and customer satisfaction goals

ZAGG, Inc.

Team Member

June 2016 - December 2017 (1 year 7 months)

Columbus, Ohio Area

- Collaborated with supervisors and coworkers to train new employees
- Managed store opening or closing operations, including auditing cash register and counting inventory

Columbus State Community College Barista

January 2015 - June 2016 (1 year 6 months)

Columbus, Ohio Area

- Served customers with coffee drinks in a timely manner
- Managed store opening or closing operations

Cameron Mitchell Restaurants

Server Assistant

May 2014 - June 2016 (2 years 2 months)

Columbus, Ohio Area

- Assisted servers with tasks such as delivering food to serve guests better
- Organized tables in an appealing way by ensuring utensils, glasses are clean for next service

Taco Bell

Service Champ

June 2011 - September 2014 (3 years 4 months)

Columbus, Ohio Area

- Implemented a plan to serve the customers in a timelier manner at drive thru
- Trained new employees and supported existing employees with their tasks

CSL Plasma

Reception Technician

July 2013 - November 2013 (5 months)

Columbus, Ohio Area

- Assisted qualified donors in completing the screening process
- Educated new donors on the use of therapeutic products made from donated plasma

Education

The Ohio State University

Geographic Information Science and Cartography, City and Regional Planning, Geographic Information Science, City and Regional

Planning (2016 - 2018)

Columbus State Community College

Associate of Science - AS, General Studies · (2013 - 2016)